Guide to the Lamberto Pignotti Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lamberto Pignotti papers
1960-2016
GEN MSS 1493
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
27.08
(37 boxes)
The collection consists of writings, artwork, correspondence, printed material, photographs, and other papers documenting the life and work of Lamberto Pignotti. Writings include typescripts, notes, proofs, and biographical materials, as well as writings of others, notably artist manifestos relating to visual poetry. Artwork includes examples of visual poetry and collage. Correspondence includes letters, postcards, and telegrams from other Italian poets, artists, and organizations. Printed material includes clippings and exhibition catalogs, pamphlets and ephemera. Photographs consist of negatives and slides.
Pignotti, Lamberto, 1926-
Content Description
The collection consists of writings, artwork, correspondence, printed material, photographs, and other papers documenting the life and work of Lamberto Pignotti. Writings include typescripts, notes, proofs, and biographical materials, as well as writings of others, notably artist manifestos relating to visual poetry. Artwork includes examples of visual poetry and collage. Correspondence includes letters, postcards, and telegrams from other Italian poets, artists, and organizations. Printed material includes clippings and exhibition catalogs, pamphlets and ephemera. Photographs consist of negatives and slides.
Arrangement
Arranged roughly in the order in which it was received.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Box 9: Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Lamberto Pignotti
Lamberto Pignotti (born 1926) is an Italian poet, writer and visual artist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Lamberto Pignotti, Librairie Patrick Fréchet, and L'Arengario Studio Bibliographico on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2017.
Poets, Italian -- 20th Century -- Archives; Visual poetry, Italian -- 20th Century; Film negatives; Slides (photographs); Visual poetry; Poets -- Italy -- 20th Century; Pignotti, Lamberto, 1926-
- Sinestesie Varie, Tavole per cineagrafica: Immagini di lineagrafica, circa 1990s (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Contains magazine clippings of advertisements, as well as other miscellaneous materials.
- Pignotti Bigrafia, circa 1978 (Box 2)
  Contains a printed copy of Bigrafia (1978), magazine clippings of advertisements, various typescripts, and other miscellaneous materials.
- Il Medico Omeopata, no. 60, 2015-11 (Box 2)
  Contains a printed copy of the homeopathic medical journal.
- Nascita della poesia: Pallazzo Braschi, Roma, 1979-05; 2 folders (Box 3)
  Contains approximately twenty manifestos of artists and poets of the visual poetry movement. Also contains notes, and hand-written and typed correspondence.
- Correspondence, clippings, typescripts and artwork, circa 1970s; 3 folders (Box 4)
  Contains material that may relate to "Nascita della poesia."
- Nascita della poesia, circa 1977 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  Contains: newspapers and various handwritten and typed material.
- Parola / Immagine - La Scrittura - Tavole e Tipologie, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 6)
  Contains magazine and newspaper clippings, as well as various printed material.
- Le Avanguardie Espropriate, circa 1970s (Box 7)
  Contains magazine and newspaper clippings.
- Printed and exhibition material, circa 1981-2016 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  Contains: Gusto e Gusto Edizioni Officina Immagine, 1995, folio; Lamberto Pignotti - Ad Alta Voce (circa 2010); Fuluio Milani, photographic prints (circa 1981); Lamberto Pignotti - Che Cora Apparira'? (2016).
- Collages and visual poetry, circa 1960s-2000s (Box 8)
  Contains paper collages, as well as various examples of visual poetry. Newspapers, magazines and other clippings are also present, as well as photographs from the 1960s, 1970s and 1990s. Projects include "Eat Poetry," "Arrabbiati," and "In America."
  - Eat Poetry: Chewing Poems e Ostie di poesia, 1970-08 (Box 9)
    Contains an example of visual poetry, incorporating two sticks of chewing gum.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
- Publicita / Tipologie varie, circa 1970s (Box 8)
  Contains: magazine and newspaper clippings of advertments, often catagorized by themes, such as Expressionism and Futurism.
- Figure / Scritture: Companotto, circa 1980s (Box 10)
  Contains printed material and magazine clippings, with extensive marginalia.
- Progetti di mostre propuste Rai, circa 1967 (Box 10)
  Contains typescripts with hand-written corrections.
- Edizioni di poesia visiva, circa 1969; 4 folders (Box 11)
  Contains original manuscripts, typescripts and bibliographic notes. Also, contains "Ma parliamo d'Altro," and "Poesie Elettroniche."
- Correspondence, circa 1970s-1990s; 5 folders (Box 12)
  Contains letters, postcards and telegrams from various people and organizations, including: Carlo Rao, Alberto Cappi, Pietro Terminelli, Mariella Bettarini, Christian Kupchik, Giovanni Anceschi, Gilda Musa, Ubaldo Giacomucci, Jean-Marie Piemme, Giuseppe Conte, Betty Danon, Carlo Marcello Conti, Mercato del Sale, Franco Bolsi, Ennio Bonea, and others.
- Correspondence, circa 1970s-1990s; 5 folders (Box 13)
  Contains letters, postcards and telegrams from various people and organizations, including: Alberto Frattini, Giovanni Fontana, Elio Grasso, Antonino Russo, V.S. Gaudio, Galleria Bonaparte, Lucio Vetri, Fernando de Filippi, Luciano Lattanzi, Ignazio Apolloni, Gio Ferri, Comune di Ancona, Comune di Bologna, Comune "La Croce," Festa Nazionale de L'Unità, and others.
- Correspondence, circa 1970s-1990s; 3 folders (Box 14)
  Contains letters, postcards and telegrams from various people and organizations, including: Punto Zero, Comune di San Vito dei Normanni, Situazione '75, Agostino Contò, Omar Calabrese, Union of Serbian Writers, Galleria Civica d'Arte Moderna, and others.
- Author poems and notes, circa 1970s-1980s; 3 folders (Box 15)
  Contains various hand-written and typed material from authors and poets, including: Mario Socrate, Cesare Ruffato, Giuseppe Conte, Carlo Villa, Cesare Viviani, Valentino Zeichen, Franco Cordelli, Domenico Cara, Ennio Cavalli, Guido Savio, Mario Ramous, Pietro Terminelli, Paolo Turati, Lino Angiuli, Vito Riviello, Raffaella di Ambra, Gilberto Finzi, Roberto Gagno, Guido Ballo, Mario Baudino, Massimo Barone, Brandolini D'Adda, Carlo Bordini, and Mariella Bettarini, Alberto Cappi, Silvia Batisti, Patrizia Angelini, M. Angioni, Ignazio Apolloni, Adriano Accattino, Martellini, Angelo Maugeri, Felice Piemontese, Aldo Rostagno, Cesare Greppi, Roberto Linzalone, V.S. Gaudio, Giovanni Giuga, Massimo Gualtieri, and Michele Rak. Some printed material is also present.
- Il discorso confezionato - Tavole e tipologie, circa 1970s (Box 15)
  Contains newspaper and magazine clippings.
- Foto di moda - Tipologie con didascalie, circa 1970s (Box 15)
  Contains handwritten notes and clippings.
- Figure Scritture, circa 1980s (Box 15)
  Contains typescripts, with handwritten notes, as well as photocopies of various articles.
- Ricostruzione dell'universo futurista, circa 2000s (Box 15)
  Contains proof, composed of print-outs.
- Dattiloscritti, circa 1980s; 2 folders (Box 16)
  Contains corrected typescripts and hand-written notes regarding "Poesia visiva sinestesia" and "Poesia."
- "Bestseller Poems", circa 1990s-2000s; 3 folder (Box 16)
  Contains Ex Libris catalog clippings, as well as typescripts regarding experimental poetry.
- Identikit di un'idea, circa 1990s (Box 16)
  Contains corrected typescripts and photocopies.
- Scritture convergenti - Litteratura e mass media, circa 1990s (Box 16)
  Contains notes, corrected typescripts and photocopies.
- Pamphlets, leaflets and printed annoucements, circa 1960s-1990s; 2 folders (Box 17)
- Pamphlets, leaflets and printed annoucements, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 18)
- Manifesti de exposizione, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 19)
  Contains exhibition posters and material.
- Manifesti de exposizione, circa 1970s-1990s; 2 folders (Box 20)
  Contains exhibition pamphlets, cards and material.
- Contemporanea, Poesia Visiva - negatives, circa 1970s (Box 21)
  Contains eight packages of negatives.
- Schedario con foto Poesie Visive ann. 70, circa 1962-1976; 2 folders (Box 21)
  Contains note cards with images, as well as a small journal.
- Schede, circa 1963-1996; 5 folders (Box 22)
  Contains handwritten biographical notes.
- Diapositive / Slides: Poesie visive mie e du altri autori, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 22)
  Contains slides.
- Diapositive / Slides: Poesie visive mie e du altri autori, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 23)
  Contains slides, held within boxes.
- Wall World, by E. Bambi and F.S. Dòdaro - "L. Pignotti - The Romanzi", 1992-11 (Box 24 (Oversize))
  Contains two examples of oversize promotional material.
- Catalogs and printed material, circa 1970s-2010s; 3 folders (Box 25)
- Catalogs and printed material, circa 1960s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 26)
- Catalogs and printed material, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 27)
- Catalogs and printed material, circa 1960s-2010s; 2 folders (Box 28)
- Catalogs and printed material, circa 1960s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 29)
- Catalogs and printed material, circa 1960s-2000s (Box 30)
- Catalogs and printed material, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 31)
- Catalogs and printed material, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 32)
- Catalogs and printed material, circa 1970s-2000s; 3 folders (Box 33)
- Catalogs and printed material, circa 1970s-2010s; 2 folders (Box 34)
- Catalogs and printed material, circa 1990s-2010s (Box 35)
- Catalogs and printed material, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 36)
- Catalogs and printed material, circa 1970s-2010s; 7 folders (Box 37)